Guide to the Lynn Thorndike Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Lynn Thorndike Papers,
1902-1963
Thorndike, Lynn, 1882-1965.
60 linear ft. ( ca. 30,000 items in 124 boxes and 1 Flatbox; some in Mapcase).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079401
Biographical Note
Professor of history at Columbia University. Columbia University A.M., 1903; Ph.D., 1905.
Scope and Content
Papers of Thorndike, consisting of correspondence, mansucripts, diaries, notes, photocopies of medieval scientific manuscripts, glass slides, books, pamphlets, and reprints. The correspondence relates to his scholarly research and publication in the field of the history of medieval science. Also, some family and personal correspondence. One half of the collection consists of photostatic copies of manuscripts Thorndike indexed in his major work, A CATALOGUE OF INCIPITS OF MEDIAEVAL SCIENTIFIC WRITINGS IN LATIN (1963), the first draft, final copy, galley proofs, related correspondence, and extensive card files of notes used in compiling the work. There is also a typescript of the 1937 edition. Thorndike's 76 volumes of personal diaries, 1902-1963, detail his daily activities, appointments, trips abroad, and lists of reading. In addition there are his other manuscripts for journal articles and book reviews.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Texts in the History of Natural and Occult Sciences
Series II: Books
Subjects
Science--History.; Science, Medieval--Research.; Manuscripts, Latin.; Scholarly publishing.; Diaries.; Slides.; Historians.; College teachers.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1963 M-63 Thorndike, Lynn Gift
- Series I: Texts in the History of Natural and Occult Sciences
  The numbers below refer to descriptions published in Medievallia Humanistica. Volume 13, 1960 and Progress of Medieval and Renaissance Studies in the United States and Canada. Bulletin No. 20, 1949.
  - No. 1 - No. 7 (Box 1)
  - No. 8 - No. 17 (Box 2)
  - No. 18; 19; 22; 24 - 25 (Box 3)
    [For 20, 21, 23 see Mapcase]
  - No. 27, 29 - 38 (Box 4)
    [28 not received; for 39 see Mapcase]
  - No. 40 - 49 (Box 5)
  - No. 50 - 54 (Box 6)
  - No. 55 - 60; 63 - 69 (Box 7)
    [61 & 62 not received]
  - No. 71 - 75 (Box 8)
    [70 not received]
  - No. 76 - 89 (Box 9)
  - No. 90 - 98 (Box 10)
  - No. 100 - 102; 104 - 109; 111 - 119 (Box 11)
    [For 103 & 110 see Mapcase]
  - No. 120 - 125; 127 - 142 (Box 12)
    [126 not received]
  - No. 143 - 155 (Box 13)
  - No. 156 - 166; 167 - 175 (Box 14)
  - No. 176 - 190 (Box 15)
  - No. 191; 192; 194 - 204; 206 - 210; 212 (Box 16)
    [211 not received; for 193; 205; 210 see Mapcase]
  - No. 213 - 218; 220 - 226; 228 - 231; 234 - 244 (Box 17)
    [219 missing, see micrifilm; 232, 233 see Mapcase]
  - No. 245; 246; 248 - 252; 254 - 262; 264 268; 270 - 272; 274; 279 - 283; 291; 293 - 295; 297 - 298 (Box 18)
    [253; 269; 275 - 277; 288 are missing see microfilm; 247; 263; 273; 278; 284 - 288; 290; 292; 296; 299 see Mapcase]
  - No. 300 - 310; 312 (Box 19)
    [311 missing see microfilm]
  - No. 313 - 322; 324; 326 - 328; 330; 331; 333 - 340; 346 - 349 (Box 20)
    [323; 325; 329; 332; 341 - 345 are missing see microfilm]
  - No. 350; 352 - 358; 360 - 369 (Box 21)
    [351 missing see microfilm; 359 see Mapcase]
  - No. 370 - 380; 383; 385 - 388; 390 - 392; 396 - 408 (Box 22)
    [381; 382; 384; 389; 395 are missing see microfilm; 393 see Mapcase]
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. First Draft [1], 1963 ed. (Box 23)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. First Draft [2], 1963 ed. (Box 24)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. First Draft [3], 1963 ed. (Box 25)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. First Draft [4], 1963 ed. (Box 26)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Final Copy [1], 1963 ed. (Box 27)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Final Copy [2], 1963 ed. (Box 28)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Final Copy [3] & miscellaneous correspondence, 1963 ed. (Box 29)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Galley Proof [1], 1963 ed. (Box 30)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Galley Proof [2], 1963 ed. (Box 31)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Index [1], 1963 ed. (Box 32)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Index [2], 1963 ed. (Box 33)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Typescript [1], 1937 ed. (Box 34)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writings in Latin. Typescript [2], 1937 ed. (Box 35)
  - Notes fro revised edition of Magic, etc. (Box 36)
  - Reprints, etc. (Box 37)
  - Articles in preparation, etc. (Box 38)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 39)
  - Ancient & medieval history (Box 40)
  - Index to 1937 (Box 41)
  - Revised draft History of Medieval Europe (Box 42)
  - Note Cards (Box 43-46)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 47)
  - Index of Herbs (Box 48)
  - Index VII & VIII (Box 49)
  - Index VII & VIII; miscellaneous (Box 50)
  - Drafts for Michael Scot (Box 51)
  - Incipits & miscellaneous (Box 52)
  - Diaries, (76 a.ms.) (Box 53)
  - Card Files: Authors AA-BRA (Box 54)
  - Card Files: Authors BREH - COR (Box 55)
  - Card Files: Authors COS - GRI (Box 56)
  - Card Files: Authors GRO - KO (Box 57)
  - Card Files: Authors KR - NA (Box 58)
  - Card Files: Authors NE - SALZ (Box 59)
  - Card Files: Authors SAM - VINC (Box 60)
  - Card Files: Authors WIND - Z (Box 61)
  - Notes for the WUS (Box 61)
  - Catch proof (Box 61)
  - Mss. catalogs (Box 61)
  - Indices of Mss. articles (Box 61)
  - Card Files: Notes on Mss., A - Florence (Box 62)
  - Card Files: Notes on Mss., Geneva - Montreal (Box 63)
  - Card Files: Notes on Mss., Padua - Peruga (Box 64)
  - Card Files: Notes on Mss., Philadelphia - A (Box 65)
  - Card Files: Bibliography 17th Century (Box 66)
  - Indices British Medic (Box 66)
  - Mss. article (Box 66)
  - Incipits, 1957 (Box 66)
  - 1960 Biz. Notes (Box 66)
  - Card Files: Photostats (Box 67)
  - Card Files: Notes on "Romance of the Rose" and Juvenal (Box 68)
  - Card Files: Notes on "Romance of the Rose" and Juvenal (Box 68)
  - Card Files: Notes on authors, A - G (Box 69)
  - Card Files: Notes on authors, H - Z (Box 70)
  - Card Files: Dates - 1660 (Box 71)
  - Card Files: Dates 1660 - (Box 72)
  - Card Files: Notes, A - Barth (Box 73)
  - Card Files: Notes, Barto - Comets (Box 74)
  - Card Files: Notes, Comp - Gan (Box 75)
  - Card Files: Notes, Comp - Gan (Box 75)
  - Card Files: Notes, Gar - I (Box 76)
  - Card Files: Notes, J - Mar (Box 77)
  - Card Files: Notes, Mas - Plab (Box 78)
  - Card Files: Notes, Pling - St. (Box 79)
  - Card Files: Notes, Sur - Z (Box 80)
  - Card Files: Subjects, A - Cli (Box 81)
  - Card Files: Subjects, Clo - Lau (Box 82)
  - Card Files: Subjects, Pe - Z (Box 83)
  - Card Files: Subjects, Law - Pa (Box 84)
  - Card Files: MSS - Authors/Titles, A & B (Box 85)
  - Card Files: MSS - Authors/Titles, C - John G. (Box 86)
  - Card Files: MSS - Authors/Titles, Joh - Ra (Box 87)
  - Card Files: MSS - Authors/Titles, Re - Z (Box 88)
  - Card Files: 17th Cent., A - Fab. (Box 89)
  - Card Files: 17th Cent., Fac - Me (Box 90)
  - Card Files: 17th Cent., Mi - Z (Box 91)
  - Card Files: Incipits, A - Ha (Box 92)
  - Card Files: Incipits, He - Quia (Box 93)
  - Card Files: Incipits, Quib - Z (Box 94)
  - Card Files: Ancient (Box 95)
  - Card Files: Roman (Box 96)
  - Card Files: Medieval (Box 97)
  - Mailing List (Box 98)
  - 16th century (Box 98)
  - Later books on 17th century (Box 98)
  - Card Files: Miscellaneous (Box 99)
  - Card Files: Miscellaneous Typescripts (Box 100)
  - Correspondence, 1902 - 1907 (Box 101)
  - Correspondence, 1903 - 1923 (Box 101)
  - Correspondence, 1917 - 1925 (Box 101)
  - Correspondence, 1933 - 1939 (Box 102)
  - Correspondence, 1939 - 1943 (Box 102)
  - Correspondence, 1944 - 1947 (Box 102)
  - Correspondence, 1948 - 1951 (Box 103)
  - Correspondence, 1951 - 1955 (Box 103)
  - Correspondence, 1955 - 1958 (Box 103)
  - Correspondence, 1950 - 1960 (Box 104)
  - Correspondence, 1960 - 1962 (Box 104)
  - Christmas Cards, 1961 (Box 104)
  - 1924 - 1932 (Box 105)
  - June 16, 1963 - chiefly taxes and photographs (Box 105)
  - Materials before 1500 still in use, notes, lists, indices, etc. (Box 105)
  - Some in 1500 - 1800 (Box 105)
  - 1951/1952 Bibliography 17th century notes written up (Box 106)
  - Stetton & Silvestre offprints (Box 106)
  - Early offprints (Box 106)
  - Mike Scot (Box 107)
  - American Council of Learned Societies MA Academy (Box 107)
  - Short History of Civilization (Box 107)
  - Articles in process or published (Box 108)
  - Neugebauer/Zinner (Box 108)
  - Notes on 17th century authors (Box 108)
  - Reviews of magic & experimental science (Box 109)
  - Book reviews (Box 109)
  - 16th century (8 x 10 notes), etc. mostly combined in IV-VI (Box 109)
  - Magic IX Medicine (Box 110)
  - MacMillan Co. correspondence (Box 110)
  - Historical Outlook articles (Box 110)
  - Miscellaneous 1950s/1960s (Box 111)
  - Secondary schools (History, Latin, English)/University administration (Box 111)
  - Reprints (Box 112)
  - Old notes mainly written up not from mss., arranged alphabetically (Box 112)
  - Correspondence re. Vols I & II of Magic & Experimental Science (Box 113)
  - General articles on MA & Early Modern Times: Essays in the History of Science (Box 113)
  - Alchemy (Box 113)
  - Lectures, 2nd half (Box 114)
  - Historiography 16th-18th centuries (Box 114)
  - France mms. catalogs by cities (Box 114)
  - Notes on mss. (no matters after 1500 now in this file) (Box 114)
  - Hist. 231 (Box 115)
  - Letters current to 1961 (Box 115)
  - Article in preparation (Box 115)
  - Houghton Mifflin re. History of Magic (Box 116)
  - Rufinus Rotograph notes, etc. (Box 116)
  - Hist. 223 (suppl. or dup. material) (Box 117)
  - Family letters (Box 117)
  - Notes on 236 (Box 117)
  - Books published with C.U. Press (Box 118)
  - 1964 Typed 568-1247 (Box 118)
  - Proofs VII - VIII (Box 118)
- Series II: Books
  - History of Magic & Experimental Science, III - VI (Box 119)
  - Science and Thought in the 15th Century (Box 119)
  - The Sphere of Sacrobosco and its Commentators (Box 119)
  - History of Astrology, Astronomy, and Mathematics (Box 119)
  - Studies in Medieval Latin Mss. 4 volumes (Box 120)
  - Essays in Intellectual History (Box 120)
  - Papers in Early Modern History (Box 120)
  - Article on the History of Medicine, 1953-1959 (Box 120)
  - Reprints Through 1937 3 volumes (Box 120)
  - Reprints Through 1937 3 volumes (Box 120)
  - Offprints IV - VII 4 volumes (Box 121)
  - Papers on the History of Medicine, 1940 (Box 121)
  - Medieval Intellectual History (Box 121)
  - Manuscripts and Research (Box 121)
  - Renaissance (Box 121)
  - Miscellaneous Early Modern (Box 121)
  - History and Geography (Box 121)
  - Medieval History and Political Thought (Box 121)
  - History of Medicine (Box 121)
  - History of Alchemy (Box 121)
  - History of Astronomy and Mathematics (Box 122)
  - Aristotle - Alchemy (Box 122)
  - History of Science by George Sarton (Box 122)
  - History of Magic and Experimental Science Volume II (Box 122)
  - History of Magic and Experimental Science Volume I (Box 122)
  - History of Magic and Experimental Science Volume II (Box 122)
  - History of Magic and Experimental Science Volume I1 (Box 122)
  - History of Magic and Experimental Science Volume III (Box 122)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writing in Latin (Box 122)
  - Incipits of Medieval Scientific Writing in Latin Notebook Mss. (Box 123)
  - General notebook [Mss.] (Box 123)
  - Economics notebook [Mss.] (Box 123)
  - Glass Plate Negatives [3 boxes] (Box 123)
  - Verreichnis... by E. Zinner, 1925 (Box 123)
  - Wesleyan University Scrapbook (Box 570)